David K. Udall papers, 1847-1988
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
David K. Udall papers, 1847-1988
MS 294
Udall, David King, 1851-1938
The strength of this collection consists of the rich family correspondence, especially with Pearl Udall Nelson; biographical and genealogical information about the Udalls; and the Mormon settlement of Saint Johns, Arizona. David K. Udall is substantially portrayed in his mission diaries, in his trial and imprisonment, and in his business activities
3 feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
None.
Biographical Note
David King Udall was born on September 7, 1851 in Saint Louis, Missouri, as his parents emigrated to Utah from their native England. He grew up in Nephi, and married Eliza Luella Stewart (1855-1937, known as Ella) of Kanab. He then took up his first mission for the Mormon Church by laboring in England from 1875 to 1877. Returning to Utah, he moved to Kanab in 1878 where he engaged in business with his wife's family.
Ordained a Bishop in June 1880, he was called to lead a colony of Mormons to Saint Johns, a small settlement of Americans and New Mexican Hispanics in northeastern Arizona Territory. There he engaged in a wide variety of activities to provide for the development of the community and his homestead. He married his plural wife, Ida Hunt (1858-1915), in 1882.
Jailed on a sham perjury charge in 1885, he returned to serve his community by developing better roads, contracting mail service, establishing a local school, and representing the area as a member of the 20th territorial legislature. Until his death in 1938, David K. Udall, together with Ella, served his church in Arizona in many capacities, as president of Saint Johns Stake and as President of the Arizona Temple in Mesa.
His children by Ella were Stewart, Pearl, Erma, Mary, Luella, David, Levi, Paul, and Rebecca. His children with Ida were Pauline, Grover, John, Jesse, Gilbert and Don. For additional information on his life see Arizona Pioneer Mormon: David King Udall his story and his family.
Organization
This collection is organized into eight series
Series I: Biographical and Historical Information, ca. 1880-1988
Series II: Correspondence, 1847-1949
Series: III: Diaries, 1875-1933
Series IV: Trial Files, 1885-1886
Series V: Reminiscences, 1932-1960s
Series VI: Business Files, 1872-1936
Series VII: Map, 1902
Series VIII: Printed Materials, 1855, 1899
Series IX: Materials held by the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-Day Saints, Archives Division, relating to David K. Udall, 1829-1910
Scope and Content Note
The strengths of this collection consists of the rich family correspondence, especially with Pearl Udall Nelson; biographical and genealogical information about the Udalls; and the Mormon settlement of Saint Johns, Arizona. David K. Udall is substantially portrayed in his mission diaries, in his trial and imprisonment, and in his business activities.
There is less documentation on his life before 1880 and after 1930, on his roles as President of the Arizona Temple, as developer of schools and roads, as legislator, and as voice for his autobiography. There is little information on the endeavors of Ella and Ida Udall, and on the lives of many family members. There are few photographs of either family gatherings or of scenes from Apache County.
Access Terms
Udall, David King, d1851-1938 - Archives
Nelson, Pearl Udall
Udall family - Archives
Stewart family - Genealogy
Hunt Irrigation Co.
Mormons - Arizona - History
Missionaries - England - Diaries
Trials (Perjury) - Arizona
Apache County (Ariz.) - History
Saint Johns (Ariz.) - History
Correspondence
Diaries
Ledgers
Related Material
See also Levi S. Udall Papers, MS 293, and Stewart L. Udall Papers, AZ 372
Container List
- Biographical and Historical Information. ca. 1880-1988
  Contains biographical and genealogical information on members of the Udall family, beginning in the early 18th century, but focusing on those descended from David Udall (1829-1910). Also includes information on family reunions; certificates awarded to David Udall and David K. Udall; photographs; comments from Elma Udall and Rex Lee at the presentation ceremony of the papers to the University in 1988; and miscellaneous historical files relating to the Saint Johns Stake and surrounding Apache County, Arizona.
  - Family Tree, pedigree charts, and research notes by Elma Udall and Geoffrey Copus. ca. 1974-1977 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - David K. Udall. 1920s-1930s (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Eliza Luella Stewart Udall. 1920s-1961 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Children and 50th Wedding anniversary. 1920s-1970s (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Estate papers of Joseph Udall. 1941-1948 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Family reunions and organizations. 1934-1988 (Box 1, Folder 6-8)
  - Certificates. 1877-1922 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Presentation of Udall Papers. 1988 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Photograph: David and Eliza Udall. 1850 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Photograph: First group of ordained workers, Arizona Temple, Mesa, includes David K. Udall; Lyman Dam overflow. 1927, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Historical materials: Saint Johns Stake. ca. 1940-1970 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Historical Materials: St. Johns / Apache County. 1940-1970 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Correspondence. 1847-1949
  Contains handwritten, typed and photocopied letters to D.K. and Ella Udall mostly from their siblings, children and extended family members in Arizona and Utah.
  The most detailed family correspondent is Pearl Udall Nelson (1880-1950). Her letters to home recount her daily experiences from childhood through adulthood including visits to her grandparents home in Kanab; attendance at church services and meetings; visits with relatives; travels and education in Utah, Arizona, and California; her osteopathic practice in Mesa and Salt Lake City; and her life with husband Joseph Nelson and stepchildren.
  Other correspondents include members of the Pace, Stewart, Tenney, and Wimmer families, John D. Lee, David Udall, Ida Hunt Udall, and cousin Alice White.
  Of interest also are letters from leaders of the Latter-Day Saints church, including Francis M. Lyman, John Taylor, Wilford Woodruff, George Reynolds, Lorenzo Snow, Heber J. Grant, and Joseph F. Smith, to Bishop David K. Udall relating to the settlement and management of the Saint Johns Stake in Arizona.
  Additional correspondence is found in the Biographical, Trial, and Business Files.
  - Nelson, Pearl Udall. 1918-1946 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Callisson, Maud Pace. 1897-1923 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Church of Jesus Christ of Latter Day Saints. 1875-1935 (Box 2, Folder 3-7)
  - Mariger, Sarah Stewart. 1883-1902 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Nelson, Joseph and George. 1920-1949 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Nelson, Pearl Udall. 1893-1917 (Box 2, Folder 10-17)
  - Nelson, Pearl Udall. 1918-1946 (Box 3, Folder 1-6)
  - Pace Family. 1911-1929 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Sherwood, Erma Udall. 1921 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Smith, Pauline Udall. 1908-1923 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Stewart Family. 1872-1934 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Stewart Levi. 1870-1875 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Stewart, Tommy. 1885-1930 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Tenney Family. 1880-1933 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Udall, David. 1847-1849, 1875-1908 (Box 3, Folder 14-15)
  - Udall, David K. 1874-1936 (Box 3, Folder 16-19)
  - Udall, David K. Jr., and Aurora M. 1908-1936 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Udall, Eliza Luella (Ella) Stewart. 1875-1937 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Udall, Ida Hunt. 1889-1911 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Udall, Jesse. 1918-1941 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Udall, Joseph. 1855, 1899 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Udall, Lela Lee. 1921-1949 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Udall, Levi S., and Louisa Lee. 1899-1923 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Udall, Louisa. 1876 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Udall, Mary. 1880 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Udall, Rebecca. 1875-1905 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - White, Alice. 1912-1946 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Wimmer family. 1898-1900 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - General, A-Z. 1874-1940 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Unidentified. 1870-1935 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Postcards and miscellaneous. 1873-1940 (Box 4, Folder 15)
- Diaries. 1875-1933
  Contains seven handwritten diaries of D.K. Udall. The first briefly outlines various jobs such as stock deliveries or construction work, and recounts an 1878 trip to Kanab. The next four are detailed accounts of his activities while on mission for his church in England from April 1875 to June 1877, and his return to Utah. The 1876-1877 volume lists his priestly endeavors of baptisms and confirmations, some family genealogical information, and several clippings from English newspapers about Mormon meetings. The sixth diary is sporadic and covers his farming activities in Apache county in 1898, and then has short entries for 1921 and 1933.
  The seventh diary is a record of his trial in Prescott, imprisonment in Detroit, and return home in December 1885. There is a typescript copy titled "Brief Journal in Prison" which was prepared by Pearl Nelson in 1932. Her copy varies slightly in places from the originals.
  There is also a microfilm copy (from the Latter-Day Saints, Archives Division) of David Udall's diary in Box 8 which documents in brief entries his marriage, emigration to Utah from England, and family, church, and farming activities from 1851 to 1910. A typescript copy of this diary, supplied by Elma Udall, is also present.
  - Diaries. 1875-1898 (Box 5, Folder 1-6)
  - Trial and prison diary. 1885 (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Trial Files. 1885-1886
  Contains handwritten letters, statements, trial transcript, presidential pardon, and clippings. The letters are from Udall's lawyer, John A. Rush; prison superintendent, John Nicholson; and several Mormon friends. The trial and pardon statements are by D.K. Udall, his attorneys, the prosecuting attorney, and the clerk of the 3rd district court; also present are notes on the trials by Levi S. Udall. The pardon was granted by Grover Cleveland.
  - Letters, statements, notes. 1885-1886, 1950s (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Trial transcript. August 3-5, 1885 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Pardon. 1885 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Clippings. 1885 (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Reminiscences. 1932-1960s
  Contains typewritten and handwritten recollections by D.K. Udall and others. Udall's concern his mail contracts between 1881 and 1920, and his memories of William Paxman, Lot Smith, and John W. Young. The remaining narratives and notes relate to the Berry family; Evans Coleman on cowboy chuck-wagons; J.N. Heywood's childhood in Alpine, Arizona; Don Lorenzo Hubbell; and "a Trip to the Grand Canyon" by George A. Udall.
  - Udall, David K. 1932-1935 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Berry, Rachel, Evanss Coleman, and others. 1930s-1960s (Box 6, Folder 7)
- Business Files. 1872-1934
  Contains handwritten and photocopied correspondence, legal records, financial records and related materials involving D.K. Udall. The general file covers mainly his bankruptcy case, and the formation and operation of Lyman Reservoir Company, Lyman Land Company, and Lyman Irrigation Company.
  The townsite documents relate to the Mormon settlement near Saint Johns, including the bill of sale and deed to property and water rights to Ammon Tenney and Udall from the Barth brothers. Also present is a letter protesting the Mormon settlement from Marcos Baca y Padia, Lorenzo Hubbell and others, and Udall's reply. There are also two ledgers, with indexes, to D.K. Udall's business and mail accounts; and a minute book and stock book to the Hunt Irrigation Company.
  - General. 1897-1934 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Udall homestead and land applications. 1872-1912 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - St. Johns Townsite. 1879-1880 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Ledger. ca. 1910-1925 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Ledger (mostly mail accounts). ca. 1915-1920 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Minute book: Hunt Irrigation Co. 1914-1918 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Stock book: Hunt Irrigation Co. 1914-1936 (Box 7, Folder 4)
- Map. 1902
  Survey and legal description for Udall Reservoir, handwritten, on linen paper.
  - Map. 1902 (Box 7, Folder 5)
- Printed Materials, 1855, 1899
  An early Mormon catechism, and a biographical yearbook with photographs, autographs, and general information of the Arizona state legislature in 1899.
  - Catechism for children exhibiting the prominent doctrines of The Church of Jesus Christ Of Latter Day Saints by Elder John Jacques. Liverpool: F.D. Richards. 1855 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Arizona's Twentieth Legislature, by James H. McClintock, Phoenix, Arizona. 1899 (Box 7, Folder 7)
- Materials held by the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-Day Saints, Archives Division, relating to David K. Udall. 1829-1910
  - David Udall to William Doust. 1847-1849 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Journal of David Udall. Includes microfilm copy, and typescript transcription by Elma Udall. 1851-1910 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Collected letters of the D.K. Udall Family. 2 Volumes. 1859-1935 (Box 8, Folder 3)